Inventory of the Jonathan Boucher Papers, 1759-1803
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Letters from the Rev. Jonathan Boucher to the Rev. John James [1729-85; D.N.B.; Headmaster of St. Bees School, Whitehaven, Cumberland; from 1771, Rector of Arthuret and Kirk Andrews.]
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John] James, Arthuret, near Carlisle, Cumberland, [Eng.] 23 Oct[obe]r 1776, 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/35). (Box-folder 1:8)
    Knows most of the American generals, including Washington, but thinks rather poorly of them; their successes, which are probably exaggerated, are due to illmanagement by the British; Mrs. Boucher is worried about her brother, an officer in the Continental Service, who may have been at Long Island; the Governor of Maryland, now Sir Robert Eden, has come to England; Boucher has been hanged and shot in effigy in America, but his servants & slaves have remained loyal; he foresees difficulties in store for him when America has been reduced, but believes that his future lies there. A friend of his, a hosier who is "as good a scholar and theologist almost, as a Bishop", has written a pamphlet in answer to a Whiggish sermon of Dr. Watson of Cambridge [the hosier is Williams Stevens: see B/3)].
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John] James 21 Nov[embe]r 1776, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/36) (Box-folder 1:8)
    Property of churchman in New York suffered in the fire but Dr. Cooper's College was not burned; Property of the [Anglican] Church and churchman expressly targeted; many of Boucher's rebellious Maryland parishioners have suffered in the war; no accommodation can be reached until the rebellion is crushed. Boucher has had some pecuniary reward from the Administration for various writings he has published but still hopes for preferment; offers board and lodging for the winter for one of James' sons; although his sister and her husband have not paid their rent, he does not wish the lease to be given to anyone else.
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John] James. 25 Jan[ua]ry 1777, 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/37). (Box-folder 1:8)
    His sister and her husband are still in financial difficulties but he wishes the lease renewed and is sending them £20 to buy new stock. He has completed a pamphlet on America and hopes the Government may reward him. The British in America seem irresolute and shilly-shallying. Both Clinton and the Howes have offered pardons to rebels; New Jersey regiment has taken offer. A horrid business at Bristol; suspicion fall on Americans & Patriots; Boucher blames "fanatical Republicans." Literary comments.
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John James] 25 Feb[ruary] 1777, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/38). (Box-folder 1:8)
    Is now resolved not to give a new lease to his brother-in-law; he has a very low opinion of him, and of his sister for marrying him. Has read a translation of the New Testament by Edward Harwood [D.N.B.] who is part of the Priestley, Price, Evans corps, but thinks it "coxcomical"; his own pamphlet needs rewriting. Dr. Cooper's Oxford sermon is excellent, and the new Archbishop of York [William Markham] has spoken out for the American church; advises James not to buy The Spirit of Athens a piece of nonsense by William Young [D.N.B.]. The American situation is not promising; "the check and defeat of the Hessians"; flight of [Rev.] Mr. [Henry] Addison's curate from Maryland; he is resigned to the loss of his property but fears for his friends.
  - J[onathan] B[oucher], Paddington Green, [Eng.] to [John] James 8 Sept[embe]r 1777, 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/39). (Box-folder 1:8)
  - J[onathan] B[oucher] to [John James] *[18 Oct. 1777], 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/40). (Box-folder 1:9)
    The troubles of his sister and her husband, "two idle, lounging people", increase, but he cannot desert them. News from America is better, but had the war not been mismanaged, the Rebellion would have been crushed. Submission of counties in three states to the Kinn's law. He hopes to return; has seen his own library, valued at 1000, offered for sale in an American newspaper and notice of a call for a meeting at "Mr. Harrison's Chapel" formerly Boucher's in a Maryland paper.
  - 23 Dec[embe]r 1777 [tha]n Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John James], 8 pp. ALS. (A/1/41). (Box-folder 1:9)
    Thanks James for his help in the Tordiffs' troubles which seem incomprehensible. The situation in America has deteriorated; the rebels are scoundrels, the Indians are more civilized; many of the leaders, and two- thirds of Washington's army are not Americans. The British Government is rotten at the core, and speeches in Parliament are seditious and treasonable. Is interested in the writing of local history of Cumberland and study of dialects; North America has a pure and uniform pronunciation of the English tongue; distress over Burgoyre's defeat [Saratoga].
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [Mr. John] James, Arthuret, [Eng.] 24 Nov[embe]r 1778, 3 pp. ALS. (A1/42). (Box-folder 1:9)
    Has applied for post of Under Secretary of the Society for the Propogation of the Gospel [a post with £80 p.a. which he secured in 1779] and is being supported by Archbishop Cornwallis of Canterbury; praises James' second son John; invites James and his wife to stay with him; is unable to help James with newspapers; gives details of air pumps with cups and balls about which James was inquiring.
  - J[onathan] B[oucher] to [John James] 11 Sept[embe]r 1779, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/43). (Box-folder 1:9)
    A worthy lady of his acquaintance may take in Kitty Strange [a protegee of Boucher and James] when she comes to London. His school, for which he has little enthusiasm, has only nine pupils, when this number rises to twelve, he will call in an assistant, preferably John James, who has been helping to prepare some of his writings for publication. If the Bishop [of Carlisle, Edmund Law 1703-87] dies, does James think he will be succeeded by Dr. Graham?
  - J[onathan] B[oucher] to [John James] [10 Nov 1779] (date in pencil), 4 pp. ALS. (incomplete). (A/1/44). (Box-folder 1:9)
    Refers once more to the project of John James' coming to help him at his school. He feels he has wasted his efforts writing "a thousand political squibs" and is considering publishing a book of sermons; asks James for some contributions. Mr. Bassenthwaite, who has a school and parish on the Island of Tortola, is looking for an assistant. Nelly's rheumatism is bad, but her physician Dr. Moore is hopeful. Boucher was unable to fore the result of the American war; "If the Rebels seem to have been more successful, they owe it not to their superior wisdom, but superior villainy. And yet, from Howe to Koppel, I firmly believe, all our misfortunes are owing to the incapacity of our Commanders..... Thirteen Colonies, the majority of whose inhabitants wished not to be so lost, yet have been lost." Probably the French and certainly the Spanish have fared worse than Britain. His affairs in Maryland like the times have turned "Topsy Turvy."
  - J[onathan] B[oucher], Paddington, [Eng.] to [John James] 12 Febr[uar]y 1780, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/45) (Box-folder 1:10)
    Tom James, who has been ill, is now much better. Boucher believes that John James is profiting by his visits to his household; he has a very high opinion of his ability and hopes he may get a studentship at Christchurch; he intends to petition his Rector for this [Richard Browne, Rector of Paddington, Reglus Professor of Hebrew & Lord Almoner's Professor of Arabic]. He has met Kitty Strange and detects weakness of character. Has been advising Mr. Charles Daubeny, [see Charles Daubeny to Boucher] on a pamphlet he is writing, but fears he has done no good; he sends James some of the works of his friend Mr. Jones [William Jones of Nayland, D.N.B.]; illness among his scholars is causing him grave anxiety.
  - J[onathan] Boucher, Paddington, Eng., to [John] James, Arthuret, near Carlisle, [Eng.] 8 March 1780, 2 pp. ALS. (A/1/46). (Box-folder 1:10)
    His hopes of obtaining a studentship for John have failed; Dr. Browne has written a very curt refusal; he fears that John will be very disappointed and suggests applying to the Archbishop of York.
  - J[onathan] Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John] James, Arthuret, near Carlisle, [Eng.] 18 March 1780, 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/47). (Box-folder 1:10)
    John has written a cheerful letter enclosing a list of the canons of Christchurch, and their connections, to whom applications might be made; Boucher himself could speak to the Archbishop of York, and the Bishop of London [Robert Lowth 1710-87]. He has recommended John to try for the Prize Poem. London has been in a panic about a change of ministry, which did not take place. "Daily waiting for great news from [Sir Henry] Clinton."
  - J[onathan] Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John] James, Arthuret, near Carlisle, [Eng.] 27 Ap[ri]l 1780, 3 pp. ALS. (A/1/48). (Folder 1:10)
    Dr. Browne [Rector of Paddington] is dead; with the help of the Bp. of Bangor [Robert Moore] Boucher wrote to the Bp. of London but the living had already been promised to Mr. Hayter, a scholar, nephew of a former Bp. of London. Boucher has been ill so he has not yet ordered the books on James' list; last week there was a sale of the books of the Dissenter Furneaux [D.N.B.] who is confined in a mad-house. Kitty Strange has a singular giddiness about her; he has not been able to find a place for her sister, Betty.
  - J[onathan] B[oucher], [Paddington, Eng.] to [John James] 20 Jul[y 1780], 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/49). (Box-folder 1:10)
    He and his wife are both in ill health; he hopes for preferment from the Bp. of London who lately recommended him as tutor to Lord Garlies, eldest son of the Earl of Galloway. Mr. Addison has unexpectedly decided to return to America and wants Boucher to lend him money.
  - J[onathan] B[oucher] to [John James] Dec[em]b[e]r 1780, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/50). (Box-folder 1:10)
    Tom is well though not very happy in his present employment. Boucher has heard Oxford news from the President of Magdalen [George Horne, later Bp. of Norwich, D.N.B.]; Oxford seems given over to frivolity; it may be very difficult to get a studentship for John at Christchurch. Jinny has taken charge of Betty Strange, who may be apprenticed to a mantua-maker; his opinion of Kitty has improved and he may employ her in his house. The situation in America now seems more hopeful. Prospect of Maryland being recovered because of quarrels amongst its leaders. Has received many letters favorable to his wishes concerning America. Washington has asked to be remembered to him, and a neighbour in Mayland is making overtures; the library of Tophan Beauclerk is to be sold, "it is said to be the largest and best ever exposed to sale"; catalogues will be printed and sold after Christmas. Boucher's school is diminishing, and will soon be reduced to eight pupils.
  - J[onathan] B[oucher], Paddington, [Eng.] to [John James] Jan[ua]ry 1781, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/52) (Box-folder 1:11)
    His school has lost three pupils but is to receive three more, including Mr. Ashley [later 6th Earl of Shaftesbury] his need for an assistant is urgent but he will be hard to please; John's friend Goldie [?Mr. Golding, Boucher's curate at Epsom] may be suitable, but not his friend Barrow. The Bouchers are moving to a larger house and will employ Kitty Strange as Upper Maid, though he dislikes the thought of having her a servant to him. He is sending James Knox's Essay on Education. Lord North forgot to ask the King for the Deanery of Bristol for Dr. Horne [later Bp. of Norwich], but the King says he shall have something as good, if not a little better.
  - J[onathan] Boucher, Paddington, [England] to [John James] 15 March 1781, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/53). (Box-folder 1:11)
    He is chilled by a pedantic letter from Mr. Lewis of Jesus, but may try him as an assistant. Betty Strange has written to Kitty that she likes her new place 'hugeously'; he believes he owes James £3 15s.4d. for the sisters' expenses. He intends to buy land to add to his Blencogo estate, and asks James to stand surety for him. Property in Maryland is still intact. Threatened but protected by his lawyer via a "sham sale." Admiral Rodney's success has not made him over optimistic; he wishes it had been the French, rather than the Dutch, that had been beaten. He has read a publication on the Sacrament by Dr. Bell [William Bell, D.N.B.] but finds it illogical.
  - J[onathan] Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John James], Arthuret, [Cumberland, Eng.] 9 Sept[embe]r 1781, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/51). (Box-folder 1:11)
    Horseback riding and warm baths improve Nelly's health. Term begins again at his school and John James will be leaving [for Oxford]; Queen's is unfit to train him; Boucher would like him to accompany a young man of fortune on the Grand Tour, and to go more into company. Points out the advantages to James and his family in moving to London. Tom will send some of his sermons, concerning the American War, intended for publication, for James to read; will Mrs. James look out for a cook.
- Boucher to John James, the younger [educated Queen's College, Oxford; assistant and partner at Boucher's school; 1785, Rector of Arthuret; died 1786 as the result of a riding accident.]
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Paddington, [Eng.] to [John James, Jr.] 14 Aug[us]t 1780, 4 pp. ALS. (A/1/54). (Box-folder 1:12)
    It is difficult to paint pure, perfect and unmingled beauty without a foil; Annapolis friend who drew his wife in the act of suckling her child which he found "inexpressibly pleasing". John should pour out his thoughts on papers. Boucher has read Thelyphthora, a book recommending polygamy by Madan, Chaplain of the Lock Hospital [D.N.B.]. Will John ask his mother to look out for a cook for his household. Mr. Addison and his son have sailed for America. Settlement with Mr. Addison. Remarks American affairs are sadly confused.
- Boucher to Rev. Mr. Tickell, Rector of Trinity Parish, Louisa County
  - Jonathan Bouche[r], P[or]t Royal, [Va.] to [Joseph] Tickell, Louisa County, [Va.] 16 Dec[embe]r 1762, 3 pp. ALS. (A/2/1). (Box-folder 1:13)
    He reproaches Tickell for not answering his letter. A box containing letters to them both from home was on board the Welcome, which was lost in Spain; it falls to him to inform Tickell that his mother and his eldest sister are both dead. Boucher's friend Tom Robinson has been killed in Germany.
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, King George [Co., Va.] to [Joseph] Tickell, Trinity Parish, Louisa County, [Va.] 13 Jan[ua]ry 1764, 3 pp. ALS. (A/2/2). (Box-folder 1:13)
    He urges Tickell to take better care of his health, and recommends cold baths; his own health is improved by the pure, thin air of Virginia. When their Indian neighbours have buried the hatchet, he and Tickell may be able to visit the famed springs of Augusta; they might then go on to visit Maury [see Boucher to Maury].
  - Boucher, Port Royal, [Va.] to [Joseph Tickell] 28 Jan 1764, 1 p. ALS. (A/2/3). (Box-folder 1:13)
    Joe Messenger of Park Gate, near Wigton, has bought some letters from home for Tickell. Messenger knows Greek, Latin and Figures and has been warmly recommended by Boucher's father & Mr. Blair; the good people of Cumberland seem to think a man may jump into preferment in America.
  - [Jonathan] Boucher, St. Mary's [Parish, Carolina Co., Va.] to [Joseph] Tickell, Louisa [County, Va.] 22 Jan[ua]ry 1765, 3 pp. ALS. (A/2/4). (Box-folder 1:13)
    He has been very busy; neither the weather nor his state of health have been able to rescue him from riding about on dirty errands. Tickells' former patron, Dr. Brown [John Brown, D.N.B.] has published some sermons. Boucher asks Tickell to recommend Mr. Messenger to Mr. Thomlinson as an assistant in Carolina. Has plans of becoming a planter.
- Boucher to Sir Frederick Morton Eden [1766-1809; D.N.B.; son of Sir Robert Eden, former Governor of Maryland; author of The State of the Poor.], (A/3).
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Epsom, [Eng.] to Sir Frederick [Morton Eden] 3 Nov[embe]r 1786, 2 pp. ALS. (A/3/1). (Box-folder 1:14)
    While Eden was in Paris, police discipline made him write, but since his return to England, Boucher has had no letter. He invites Eden and his friend Deverell of Oriel to spend Christmas with him. He has sent him a letter introducing Mr. Zimmermann of Brunswick.
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Epsom, [Eng.] to Sir Fred[eric]k M[orton] Eden, Christ Church, Oxford, [Eng.] 7 Febr[ua]ry 1787, 1 p. ALS. (A/3/2). (Box-folder 1:14)
    He instructs Eden on the correct way to draw up a note of band. Mr. Watson [probably John, brother of Joshua Watson] is to go to University College.
  - [tha]n Boucher to [Sir] Fred[eric]k M[orton] Eden 16 Sept[embe]r 1788, 1 p. ALS. (A/3/3). (Box-folder 1:14)
    He is much shaken [by the death of his second wife on 14 Sep] and is to go to Carlisle for a month; as his servant John will now be out of a place, he suggests that Eden recommend him to Mrs. Moore [his aunt, wife of the Archbishop of Canterbury].
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Carlisle, [Eng.] to Sir Frederick M[orton] Eden, London, [Eng.] 16 Oct[obe]r 1793, 3 pp. ALS. (A/3/4). (Box-folder 1:14)
    On his way to Edinburgh on horseback, he composed a series of epigrams on Scottish dress, churches, towns, etc., none of which impressed him favourably. He received a most flattering reception in Edinburgh, but will not yet disclose his reason for going there. [He had hopes of a Scottish bishopric.] He has visited Hawthornden where the poet Drummond lived. Suggests he and Eden take a tour of Scotland and publish a book to "bear our expences [sic]."
  - [Jonathan Boucher], Epson, [Eng.] to Sir Fred[eric]k M[orton] Eden, Lincoln's Inn Fields, London, [Eng.] 13 Nov[embe]r 1793, 3 pp. AL. (A/3/5). (Box-folder 1:14)
    His journey from Carlisle took fifty-four hours. The Edinburgh scheme needs consideration and reflection before it is discussed at Lambeth; the Archbishop's approval is essential. He wishes to discuss Eden's future plans with him and warns him to "take care only to pass through life, as I have done, [without] ever finding out what I was fit for."
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Epsom, [Eng.] to Sir Fred[eric]k M[orton], Eden, at the Hon[ora]b[le] Lady Eden's in Queen's Square, Bath, [Eng.] [8 January 1794], 3 pp. ALS. (A/3/6). (Box-folder 1:14)
    Jona[tha]n Boucher, Epsom, [Eng.] to Sir Fred[eric]k M[orton], Eden, at the Hon[ora]b[le] Lady Eden's in Queen's Square, Bath, [Eng.]. He apologizes for breaking an appointment. Sir Frederick and Lady Eden now have it in their power to render him an essential piece of justice [probably refers to the heavy loss Boucher sustained when he stood security for Sir Robert Eden]. He foresees another Revolution in France against the Jacobins. Pitt will be severely badgered this session but though he dislikes the man, he dreads a change of ministry just now.
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher to Sir Fred[eri]c[k] M[orton] Eden, London, [Eng.] 9 March 1794, 1 pp. ALS. (A/3/7). (Box-folder 1:15)
    He is coming to town with Mr. Stevens [see B/3] on Tuesday and will dine with Eden. Requests a meeting with Capt[ai]n Eden "to settle everything" at Sir Frederick's house.
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher to Sir Fred[eric]k M[orton] Eden, London, [Eng.] 20 March 1794, 2 pp. ALS. [pasted inside 9 March 1794.] (A/3/8). (Box-folder 1:15)
    He has written to the Archbishop of Canterbury about the Edinburgh business. He is coming to town and will stay with the Edens, if convenient. Thanks the Edens for their "late kindness which will make me a free man for at least a year to come."
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Epsom, [Eng.] to Sir Fred[eric]k [Morton Eden] 23 Ap[ri]l 1794, 2 pp. ALS. (A/3/9). (Box-folder 1:15)
    He is much grieved by the death of his sister [Jinny]. He is sorry that Eden is in difficulties over the house he bought, and suggests that he ask his father-in-law [James Paul Smith] for a loan, for which he will stand security.
  - J[onathan] B[oucher], Epsom, [Eng.] to Sir Fred[eric]k M[orton] Eden, London, [Eng.] 13 July 1794, 3 pp. ALS. (A/3/10). (Box-folder 1:15)
    He is glad that Eden's financial difficulties have been settled, but as his income is only £800 p.a. and his expenses at least £1000 p.a. he urges economy; however, he should remain hopeful about the future. Comments on a business arrangement with Messrs Whites in Fleet Street. He sends his good wishes to Eden's wife, who is pregnant.
  - J[onathan] B[oucher], Epsom, [Eng.] to Sir Frederick M[orton] Eden, on the Northern Circuit 14 Aug[us]t 1794, 3 pp. ALS. (A/3/11). (Box-folder 1:15)
    He hopes that Eden, who is on the Northern Circuit, has made some gleanings for is Magnum Opus [The State of the Poor]; if he is near Carlisle, he should meet Mr. Houseman who has traversed Cumberland to make agricultural reports and who is making out for Boucher an account of land in that county belonging to absentees, and of tillage etc. Boucher has estimated the Poor Rate for his own native village [Blencogo] at sixpence in the pound. He has had an agreeable visit from the Rev. Mr. Herbert Croft [later Sir Herbert Croft, D.N.B.] a fellow lexicographer. Comments that a book on "The Present State of France" is ill written and badly translated.
  - J[onathan] B[oucher] to Sir Frederick [Morton] Eden, Lincoln's Inn Fields, London, [Eng.] [May 1796], 2 pp. ALS. (A/3/12). (Box-folder 1:15)
    He declines an invitation to visit Eden until he has got through "A" [of his Glossary]. He considers Pitt's Bill [to change the Poor Law] paltry and impracticable.
  - . J[onathan] B[oucher] to Sir Frederick [Morton] Eden, Lincoln's Inn Fields, London, England 16 June 1796, 1 p. ALS. (A3/13). (Box-folder 1:16)
    He is sending some notes which Eden may be able to use in his book. Buried a Miss Boucher whose brother "wants to make it out that they & I are related."
  - Jona[tha]n Boucher, Epsom, [Eng.] to Sir Fred[eric]k [Morton] Eden, London, [Eng.] 17 June 1796, 2 pp. ALS. (A/3/14). (Box-folder 1:16)
    The bearer of this letter is Mr. Robert Jamieson, a young Scot, proficient in Gaelic, Latin & Greek, who wishes to become a bookseller; he asks Eden to speak to Messrs. Whites, the booksellers, about him.
  - J[onathan] Boucher], Epsom, [Eng.] to Sir Frederick [Morton] Eden, London, [Eng.]. 21 July 1796, 1 p. ALS. (A/3/15). (Box-folder 1:16)
    He encloses a letter containing some reflections about Pitt's Bill; Eden's book will be referred to when this Bill and the author of it are gone. Also enclosed is an account of the population of Carlisle.
  - J[onathan] B[oucher] to Sir Frederick [Morton Eden] 26 Oct. 1796, 3 pp. ALS. (A/3/16). (Box-folder 1:16)
    He has read through the papers sent to him by Eden but does not agree with his views on education, which resemble those of Dr. Priestley; he fears they may expose the whole work to censure and so, though diffident about putting forward his own notions, he has re-written this section; Eden must decide which version to use; he has also softened the critique on Mr. Pitt. He wonders what effect Burke's pamphlet [probably Letters on a Regicide Peace] will have on the public mind; the "speechifyings" in Parliament have been very poor - "this is not an age of great men."
  - J[onathan] Boucher, Epsom, [Eng.] to Sir F[rederick] M[orton] E[den] n.d. [ca. 1793?] Thurs. Evening, 2 pp. ALS. (A/3/17). (Box-folder 1:16)
    He has read through the papers concerning the uncancelled bond; as Eden cannot prove there was ever any intention of cancelling it, he has no case in a common law court, but Boucher believes he has strong enough grounds to take the case to Chancery. He is forwarding a letter from Mr. Addison to Mr. Watson. Eden's play is not to go to Sheridan who is "as little worthy to be trusted with a new play, as with money, or anything else", or to Grubb, but to young Banister; Boucher is not optimistic as to its success.